A Guide to the Papers of John Powell, 1888-1978, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series IV: Eugenics and Racial Integrity
  - Subseries D.: Eugenics news clippings
    - "Virginia Takes Up Racial Integrity," The New York Times1930 February 16, 1 p. 1st page missing (Box-folder 43:97)
      An article by Virginius Dabney,that describes the opposing views of racial integrity in Virginia. On the one hand, John Powell is protecting white people from miscegenation. Conversely, racial integrity is creating tension between the races, and some people believe that there is no risk of miscegenation.
    - "John Powell, Noted Pianist-Composer, Gives Views On Negro Music, Its Use and Abuse," The Musical Courier. 1930 May 3, 1 p. (Box-folder 43:98)
      The article is an interview of John Powell and his theories about allowing the negro to create music that is not influenced by whites.
    - "New Brown Race Discovered In U.S.," The New York Sun1931 Sept 30, 1 p (Box-folder 43:99)
      An article about a new race going back to the first white settlers of America. It is discussed in a new book, Brown America, the Story a New Race.
    - "Youth Held On Charge Of Criminal Attack" 1931, 1 p. (Box-folder 43:100)
      An article about a six year-old negro girl that was attacked by a sixteen year-old named Merritt Bragg.
    - "Senators Plan to Introduce Bills to Aid Voluntary Negro Migration," by Holmes Alexander. [1931], 1 p. (Box-folder 43:101)
      An article about Senator Langer's plans to reintroduce his bill from the last Congress (S.759) to aid Negroes who will move to Liberia and Senator Richard Russell plans to introduce a bill he offered in 1949 for aid to persons who volunteer to change States for racial reasons.
    - "Voice of the People: Colonization Proposal Denounced As Visionary." The Richmond Times-Dispatch. [1931], 1 p. (Box-folder 43:102)
      An editorial against colonization and expressing the desire to live in America and not be denied the equal rights of the Constitution.
    - "Virginia 'Nordic Blood Purist' Reveal Their Scheme to J. A. Rogers." The Norfolk Journal and Guide. [1931], 2 pp. (Box-folder 43:103)
      An article by J. A. Rogers which is basically an interview with John Powell and Earnest Sevier Cox exposing their ideas about carrying the negroes home to Africa.
    - "As It Appears To The Cavalier," The Richmond Times-Dispatch1932 February 15, 1 p. (Box-folder 43:104)
      An editorial by Thomas Lomax Hunter who does not want the Negroes to go to Africa. (Hunter writes another editorial, see 46:11)
    - "Negro Colonization Bill Opposed By Local Leader," The Richmond News Leader1932, 1 p. (Box-folder 43:105)
      An article about Gordon B. Hancock's protest against colonization.
    - "John Powell's Assertion That There Is No Real American Negro Music Disproved By Eminent Musicians And Critics," The Norfolk Journal and Guide1933 January 28, 3 pp. (Box-folder 43:106)
      Musicians, R.Nathaniel Dett, Clarence Cameron White, Ray Francis Brown, and J. Harold Brown respond that negro music is not influenced by whites.
    - "Tribute to John Powell," The Richmond Times-Dispatch1936 June 14, 1 p (Box-folder 43:107)
      An editorial praising Powell for his piano music and his preservation of Anglo-Saxon folksongs.
    - "'Ol SussexChep' Prints the Bible In His Dialect" 1942, 1 p. (Box-folder 43:108)
      An article about James Richards who translates the bible into his native Sussex dialect which resembles the language of American "Negro" spirituals.
    - "American Skill May Convert Liberian Liabilities to Assets," The Richmond Times-Dispatch1948 December 19, 2 pp. (Box-folder 43:109)
      An article about the beauty and economics of Liberia. The article also mentions Edward R. Stettinius, Jr. and Austin Brockenbrough who invested business in Liberia.
    - The Last Go-Around on Hillbilly Music, Voice of the People, The Richmond Times-Dispatch1953 October 10, 1 p. (Box-folder 43:110)
      Editorial about hillbilly music.
    - "Head of Liberian Movement Offers Emigration Plan," The Richmond News Leader1955 July 27, 1 p. (Box-folder 43:111)
      An editorial by Benjamin Gibbons, President, Universal African Nationalist Movement, about settling in Liberia and the colonization legislation of Senator Langer.
    - "School Suit Holds Key to Texas Integration," The Richmond Times-Dispatch1955 August 26, 1 p. (Box-folder 43:112)
      Texas Citizens Council filed suit to prevent the payment of State funds to any public school that desegregates and other schools are waiting to see how this lawsuit is decided.
    - "W and L Rector Raps Proposal On Race Issue," The Richmond Times-Dispatch1955 August 26, 1 p. (Box-folder 43:113)
      Washington and Lee University Rector, James R. Caskie, states that he does not want the Association of American Law Schools to have any say on who shall be admitted to the University.
    - "Finds Columnist Tucker In Mix-up on Books," The Richmond Times-Dispatch1955 August 26, 1 p. (Box-folder 43:114)
      An editorial complains that columnist, Ray Tucker's review of W. E. Debnam's new book, My Old Kentucky Home, Good Night mistakenly refers to material from another book, Weep No More, My lady
    - "Negro Educator Supports Plan For Colored Exodus," The Citizens' Council 1957 August, 3 pp. (Box-folder 43:115)
      Professor Clennon King, from a Mississippi Negro college, testified before the Senate Foreign Relations Committee as a supporter of Senator Langer's bill to move the Negroes to Africa for more security and to maintain segregation of the black race.
    - "Federal Judges Have Broad Civil Contempt Powers," The Daily Progress1957 August 27, 1 p. (Box-folder 43:116)
      An article that expresses concern that a "federal judge has civil contempt powers to force compliance with their orders in voting rights cases."
    - "Requiem After Nashville," The Richmond News Leader1957 Sept 11, 1 p. (Box-folder 43:117)
      The author of the editorial complains that the desegregated schools have violence and racial tensions that are causing harm to the children. The author adds that they had warned that this would happen. He writes, "we told you so."
    - Private Schools Have Great Tradition in Richmond," George W. Rogers, The Richmond News Leader1957 November 19, 2 pp. (Box-folder 43:118)
      Rogers comments that the one good thing that has come out of the 1954 Supreme Court decision on school desegregation is that Richmond is considering a revival of private schools. He tells the rich history of private schools in Richmond, going back to the year, 1759. He mentions the Lancaster School, The Academy of Fine Arts and Science of the United States, and the Richmond Academy for Female Education. He also mentions John Peyton McGuire and his school for boys.
    - "An Unreconstructed Southern Editor Goes to Chicago," Grover C. Hall, Jr., The Richmond News Leader1958 March 11, 1 p. (Box-folder 43:119)
      Excerpts from a talk given by the editor of The Montgomery Advertiser. Grover C. Hall, Jr., a "colorful," "Southern," and "fearless" editor writes about how the South will not respond well to desegregation. He states, "If Northern politicians, licksplitting and honey-bunching the minority voting blocs in the North, impel the Federal government to grind down upon the South one of two things may happen. Much of the South will close its schools or there will be violence."
    - "Knoll Says Integration Was Help to Washington Schools," The Daily Progress1959 February 20, 1 p. (Box-folder 43:120)
      Erwin Knoll, education writer for The Washington Post and Times-Herald writes that integration has not caused much violence and offers opportunities for schools to share assets, and have more space.
    - "The Cost of a School Solution," The Daily Progress1959 February 21, 1 p. (Box-folder 43:121)
      An editorial suggests that there is a need for the public to develop tuition grants for private segregated schools.
    - "Dure Tuition Grant Plan May Have Local Defender Backing" [1959], 1 p. (Box-folder 43:122)
      An article about Leon Dure's proposal to allow tuition grants for use in private schools for those families that want a segregated school.
    - "North Carolinian Reports on Tar Heel Pupil Placement," The Richmond News Leader[1959], 1 p. (Box-folder 43:123)
      Editorial by Philip L. Lacy who writes that North Carolina is accepting negroes in their schools and he warns that if Colgate Darden has his way, Virginia will soon be following the same path, and opening the door to intermarriage.
    - Unnamed article on the desegregation of schools. [1959], 1 p. (Box-folder 43:124)
    - Your Right To Say It, The Daily Progress [1959], 1 p. (Box-folder 43:125)
      An editorial by Ida E. R. Abernethy expressing the concern that integration will not offer anything to white children and will actually harm them.
    - "Confused City Candidates." The Richmond Times-Dispatch[1959], 1 p. (Box-folder 43:126)
      An editorial about the candidates that are running for City Council and how they don't understand the segregation proposal of Governor Byrd.
    - "Southerners And Integration" [1959], 1 p. (Box-folder 43:127)
      An article by Nell Battle Lewis (sister of Dr. Ivey Lewis) criticizing an editorial written by Sarah Patton Boyle, a faculty wife in support of integrating schools.
    - "March On Capitol to Hold Line," The Citizen's Council 1959 April, 2 pp. (Box-folder 43:128)
      An orderly crowd of 5,000 Virginians stand in front of the State Capital in Richmond calling themselves "the Bill of Rights Crusade" and protesting desegregation. The group is led by C. Benton Coiner of Waynesboro and Edward J. Silverman, a weekly newspaper editor from Blackstone.
    - The Defender, newsletter 1960, 6 pp. (Box-folder 43:129)
      A publication of The Defenders of State Sovereignty and Individual Liberties dedicated to preserving a government of laws under a written constitution.
    - "Bobby's Barefoot Burmese," The Richmond News Leader1961 May 9, 1 p. (Box-folder 43:130)
      An editorial criticizing President Kennedy and his brother, Robert Kennedy, for their assault on the State of Virginia and desegregation. The article also reports that protestors standing outside of the building where Mr. Kennedy is giving his speech are arrested.
    - "How Reds Plot To Stir Black Terror In America." The Police Gazette1961, 4 pp. (Box-folder 43:131)
      An exclusive by George McGrath about negro organizations across the country promoting black nationalism. He writes that some are violent and infiltrated with communism. The article also mentions that one of the more respectable organizations is The Nation of Islam and Malcolm X.
    - "Negroes North and South," The Savannah Pressn.d., 1 p. (Box-folder 44:1)
      An article about the tension that exists between the races in the North as well as the South.
    - "Raid On Negro Home Goes To Grand Jury." n.d., 2 pp. (Box-folder 44:2)
      An article about some attacks that were made on a house belonging to a negro, Samuel Brown, by white men.
    - "Jamestown and Plymouth." The Newport News Daily Pressn.d., 1 p. (Box-folder 44:3)
      An editorial by Richard L. Mason, Head of the History Department, College of William and Mary about the reasons why Plymouth, Massachusetts cannot use the slogan, "The Nation's Birthplace." He writes that more than a decade before pilgrims landed on Plymouth Rock, they had met at Jamestown. He also mentions the supporting work of Dr. David Saville Muzzey, of Columbia University.
    - Pocahontas article, The Daily Chroniclen.d., 1 p. (Box-folder 44:4)
      An article about the descendants of Pocahontas and The United States Ambassador presentation of two memorial windows to Princess Pocahontas.
    - Unnamed article n.d., 1 p. (Box-folder 44:5)
      Article gives a review of Dr. Gunmar Myr Day and his book, An American Dilemma
    - "Anglo-Saxon Stock." n.d., 1 p. (Box-folder 44:6)
      An editorial by Richard Chase encouraging schools, colleges, churches, and community organizations to revitalize the genuine folk songs, traditions and customs of Anglo-Saxon heritage.
    - "With Artist and Musician." n.d., 1 p. (Box-folder 44:7)
      Article describes an interview with John Powell about his views on negro music. He states that negro music is not American, but African.
    - "Urge Negro Voters To Ballot Tuesday." n.d., 1 p. (Box-folder 44:8)
      An article about the Richmond Democratic League encouraging the Negro Democratic voters to go to the polls.
    - "Enlightened Yankee Renders Orthodox Pity," The Richmond Times-Dispatchn.d., 1 p. (Box-folder 44:9)
      An editorial accuses the south of having a degenerating culture. Reference is made to all the rioting in the south. The editorial suggests that the north and west should help the negro so that the negro can in turn educate the southern brethren.
    - "Opposites Don't Attract, Says British Scientist." n.d., 1 p. (Box-folder 44:10)
      An article quoted Lord Raglan as saying, "what is happening in America is what always happens when two races occupy the same country? They always fuse."
    - "As It Appears To The Cavalier." n.d., 1 p. (Box-folder 44:11)
      An editorial by Thomas Lomax Hunter, in which he expresses his opinion that the races have already been mixed and it is very cruel to declare a person that is living as white to change to negro. He also writes that Alexander Dumas was once questioned about the race of his great-grandfather in which Dumas replied, "An ape, sir, thundered the great man? My pedigree commences where yours terminates."
    - Fragment of news clipping titled, "Says Leaders Of Two Races Should Form A Contact." n.d., 1 p. (Box-folder 44:12)
      This is an article about white writer Leo M. Favrot's idea that "the white chambers of commerce should arrange to meet and discuss community problems with colored citizens."
    - "Our Anti-Lynching Bill." n.d., 1 p. (Box-folder 44:13)
      An article about legislation by Governor Byrd that is passed in the Senate and proposes that any lynching activity is a crime against the State. This legislation reflects a revulsion for mob violence.
    - "Conference On Health Ends," The Detroit Evening Timesn.d., 1 p. (Box-folder 44:14)
      An article about the Convention of the American Public Health Association where Dr. Plecker gave a talk on "Virginia's Attempt to Adjust the Color Problem."
    - "For The Sake Of The Mothers," The Newport News Daily Pressn.d., 1 p. (Box-folder 44:15)
      An article about a bill to abolish the flogging of convicts in Virginia. The bill is argued by mothers of Virginia who are opposed to flogging. The Newport News Daily Press regards this as a strong argument to pass the bill.
    - Husband White, Woman Claims; Test Case Looms, Appeal Likely From Two-Year Term In Prison." n.d., 1 p. (Box-folder 44:16)
      An article about the indictment of 24 year-old Mary Hall for her marriage to Mott Hamilton Wood, an alleged mulatto. John Powell and Dr. W. A. Plecker are also mentioned in the article in regard to their efforts to pass legislation that defines a negro.
    - "Powell Is Asked To Define What Is Anglo-Saxon," The Worldn.d., 1 p. (Box-folder 44:17)
      An article by James Weldon Johnson, Secretary of The Negro Advancement Association who responds to Powell's article on the deterioration of the white race.
    - "Professor Raises His Voice Against Equalitarian Theory" n.d., 1 p. (Box-folder 44:18)
      An article about Dr. Henry E. Garrett, Professor of Educational Psychology at the University of Virginia who believes that negroes are inferior in their personality and mental abilities.
    - "John Powell To Speak Twice On Race Integrity," [Newport News Daily Press] n.d., 1 p. (Box-folder 44:19)
      Powell is speaking to the Woman's Constitution League and the Anglo-Saxon Newport News Club.
    - "National Art Depends Upon Real Americans." [The Norfolk Virginia-Pilot] n.d., 1 p. (Box-folder 44:20)
      An article that describes Powell's speech on a homogenous nation.
    - "Powell Is Offered $1,000 Commission." n.d., 1 p. (Box-folder 44:21)
      An article about Powell's commission to make other American Composers aware of the musical folklore in America.
    - "Powell Sees Bond of Sympathy Between England-America." n.d., 1 p. (Box-folder 44:22)
      An article quotes Powell from an interview that he gave in England after a concert.
    - "Warm Hearts on a Winter's Night." n.d., 1 p. (Box-folder 44:23)
      An article supporting the folklore and Anglo-Saxon heritage that John Powell and Richard Chase are trying to preserve.
    - "Pamunkey Indians to Discuss Question of Their Women Voting" n.d., 1 p. (Box-folder 44:24)
      Part of the article is missing.
    - "Seek Negro Who Shot 3 Roanoke Officers; 1 Dead." n.d., 1 p. (Box-folder 44:25)
      Fragment of an article.
    - "A Worth-While Sacrifice." n.d., 1 p. (Box-folder 44:26)
      An article expressing support to a woman who unknowingly married a black man.
    - "Negro's View Of Race Integrity," The Newport News Daily Pressn.d., 1 p. (Box-folder 44:27)
      An article written by a negro at The Newport News Daily Press points out that white men are the ones that are responsible for the creation of mulattoes because they had illegitimate intercourse with negro women. The Newport News Daily Press warns against race mixing and urges people to keep the races separate.
    - "Integration, Intermarriage of Races held Contrary to Law of Nature," by Henry P. Taylor to the Editor, The Richmond News Leadern.d., 1 p. (Box-folder 44:28)
      Taylor writes that "Negroes" are an inferior race and would collapse without leaning on white society. He also writes that the founding fathers possessed judgement, character, and courage which "Negroes do not have."
- Series V.: Photographs
  - John Powell 1913-1926, 9 items (Box-folder 44:29)
  - John Powell n.d., 32 items (Box-folder 44:30)
  - Colleagues, friends, and family 1903-1963, 36 items (Box-folder 44:31)
  - Old Harp Singers 1934, 2 items (Box-folder 44:32)
  - Places 1909, 4 items (Box-folder 44:33)
  - White Top Folk Festival and other festivals 1931-1939, 12 items (Box-folder 44:34)
  - Miscellaneous n.d., 2 items (Box-folder 44:35)
- Series VI.; Miscellaneous
  - Papers of John Henry Powell, Sr. 1894 February, 10 items (Box-folder 45:1)
    Biographical information for the principal of Richmond Female Seminary and two pupils, Elizabeth Wright Weddell, and Margaret Ward Weddell; a list of teachers; an essay about the school by former student and First Lady Edith Bolling Wilson; a report card for Pauline Bromm.
  - Biographical information on John Powell n.d. (Box-folder 45:2)
  - Passport of John Powell n.d., 1 item (Box-folder 45:3)
  - Illustrated sketches of John Powell n.d., 7 items (Box-folder 45:4)
  - Miscellaneous n.d. (Box-folder 45:5)
  - Music organizations 1928-1933 (Box-folder 45:6)
  - Other organizations n.d. (Box-folder 45:7)
  - The Raven Society Certificate of membership for John Powell 1913 May 12, Oversize
  - Passport of John Powell 1914 August 5, Oversize
  - Artwork. Unidentified n.d., Oversize
  - Financial. Annual statements 1950-1953, 29 items (Box-folder 46:1)
  - Financial. Bank receipts. 1927-1958, 28 items (Box-folder 46:2)
  - Financial. Contract Agreements 1908-1919, 11 items (Box-folder 46:3)
  - Financial. Contract Agreements. 29 items 1921-1929, 29 items (Box-folder 46:4)
  - Financial. Contract Agreements. 1930-1939, 67 items (Box-folder 46:5)
  - Financial. Contract Agreements 1940-1949, 21 items (Box-folder 46:6)
  - Financial. Contract Agreements 1950-1959, 5 items (Box-folder 46:7)
  - Financial. Contract Agreements 1961, 1 item (Box-folder 46:8)
  - Financial. Contract Agreements. n.d., 6 items (Box-folder 46:9)
  - Financial. Expenses 1908-1932, 43 items (Box-folder 46:10)
  - Financial. Expenses. 1933-1951 (Box-folder 46:11)
  - Financial. German receipts. 1907-1914 (Box-folder 46:12)
  - Financial. Income. 1916-1939, 45 items (Box-folder 47:1)
  - Financial. Income. 1940-1962 (Box-folder 47:2)
  - Financial. Insurance. 1935-1937; 1958, 9 items. (Box-folder 47:3)
  - Financial. Organizations. 1960-1964, 11 items (Box-folder 47:4)
  - Financial. Receipts. Personal. n.d. (Box-folder 47:5)
  - Financial. Royalty Statements. 1920-1938, 60 items. (Box-folder 47:6)
  - Financial. Royalty Statements. 1939-1960, 41 items. (Box-folder 47:7)
  - Financial. Schedules for concerts and lessons. 1918-1929, 8 items. (Box-folder 47:8)
  - Financial. Tax. 1923-1957, 7 items (Box-folder 47:9)